Guide to the Alice Catherine Evans papers, 1908-1965.
Evans, Alice Catherine papers, 1908-1965.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alice Catherine Evans papers, 1908-1965.
2552
Alice Catherine Evans, 1881-1975.
.7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, scientific speeches, articles, and reports.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of Alice C. Evans, who graduated from Cornell University in 1909 and served as a dairy bacteriologist for the United States Department of Agriculture and for the United States Public Health Service.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Alice C. Evans graduated from Cornell University in 1909 and served as a dairy bacteriologist for the United States Department of Agriculture and for the United States Public Health Service.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of correspondence, scientific speeches, articles, and reports by Alice C. Evans and others; original and revision of her memoirs; clippings, photographs, programs, and official invitations. Also, copies of extracts from Evans' correspondence with Theobald Smith (1925) concerning their disagreement about the possibility of human infection through bovine organisms; correspondence pertaining to her participation in the First and Second International Congresses for Microbiology (1930-36) and the First through Fourth Inter-American Congresses on Brucellosis (1948-57) and to her research on brucellosis and other diseases and the problem of human infection through the milk of animals, conducted during her years as dairy bacteriologist for the USDA and as a bacteriologist for the U.S. Public Health Service; and letters from Carrie Chapman Catt, Paul de Kruif, Marie Dressler, Elmer V. McCollum, Veranus A. Moore, Henry Morgenthau Jr., Bela Schick, Luther Terry, Martha van Rensselaer, Hans Zinsser, and others in medicine, science, or public life.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Evans, Alice Catherine, 1881-1975.; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947.; De Kruif, Paul, 1890-1971.; Dressler, Marie, 1873-1934.; McCollum, Elmer Verner, b. 1879.; Moore, Veranus A. (Veranus Alva), 1859-1931.; Morgenthau, Henry, 1891-1967.; Schick, Béla, 1877-; Smith, Theobald, 1859-1934.; Terry, Luther L. (Luther Leonidas), 1911-; Van Rensselaer, Martha, 1864-1932.; Zinsser, Hans, 1878-1940.; Inter-American Congresses on Brucellosis.; International Congress for Microbiology.; United States. Dept. of Agriculture.; United States. Public Health Service.
Subjects:
Bacteriology.; Cattle--Diseases.; Dairy bacteriology.; Dairying.; Dairy processing.; Milk--Bacteriology.; Milk hygiene.; Women reformers.; Women scientists.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Memoirs
  - "Memoirs" by ACE. ( 1963 ). 70 pp. xerox, bound. (Box 1)
  - "Memoirs" by ACE. ( 1965, revised and expanded from 1963). 106 pp. xerox, bound. (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - First International Congress For Microbiology (Paris, July 1930 ) (Box 1)
    Correspondence pertaining to ACE's appointment as a representative of the Society of American Bacteriologists at the Paris meeting and to her authority to visit English bacteriologists at the time of the meeting; a report of "Visits to Six European Laboratories" by ACE (5 pp. carbon typescript); "The Chronic Type of Brucelliasis," a 2 pp. typescript marked "discussion at Paris conference"; "Report on European Congresses" by ACE and Sara E. Branham (14 pp. carbon typescript); pictures, programs, official invitations, and other items relevant to the Congress. (1930, 41 pcs.).
  - Second International Congress For Microbiology (London, July 1936 ) (Box 1)
    Correspondence concerning the Congress; notes for a paper on brucellosis which ACE delivered or discussed (2 pp. handwritten on both sides); "Comments on the London Congress" (33 small pp., handwritten); official invitations, clippings, banquet menu and guest list, and other relevant items. (1936, 48 pcs.).
  - Inter-American Committee on Brucellosis (Box 1)
    Correspondence pertaining to the First Inter-American Congress for the Study of Brucellosis (Oct.-Nov. 1948, Mexico City); "The Incidence of Human Brucellosis," a paper discussed by ACE (6 pp. handwritten); correspondence pertaining to the Second Inter-American Congress for Brucellosis (Nov. 1948, Mendoza, Argentina); notes on the "Origin of the Inter-American Committee on Brucellosis and its Relation to Other Organizations for the Study of Brucellosis" (1965, 6 pp. handwritten); report of the President of the Inter-American Committee for Brucellosis (7 pp. typewritten); and other relevant issues. ([1946-1948]-1965, 59 pcs.).
  - Third Inter-American Congress on Brucellosis; First Meeting of WHO/FAO Expert Panel on Brucellosis; Committee on Public Health Aspects of Brucellosis of the National Research Council (Box 1)
    Correspondence pertaining to the above organizations; minutes of meetings of the Committee on Public Health Aspects of Brucellosis (May 1949 and Sept. 1949); report of the Committee on Public Health Aspects of Brucellosis to the Agricultural Board, Division of Biology and Agriculture, National Research Council, Washington, D.C. (Apr. 1950); Address of Welcome to the Congress by ACE, President of the Inter-American Committee on Brucellosis (Nov. 6, 1950, 5 pp. carbon typescript); a report of the meeting of the Congress and proposed resolutions, which it later adopted; a pamphlet, Joint FAO/WHO Expert Panel on Brucellosis, report on the first session (Geneva: WHO, 1951 36 pp.) (1949-1950, 70 pcs.)
  - Fourth Inter-American Congress on Brucellosis (Aug. 1957, Lima, Peru) (Box 1)
    Correspondence concerning the meeting; a program of the Congress, including a list of papers to be given; Address of the President (3 pp. carbon typescript) (1956-1957, 21 pcs.).
  - Chronic Brucellosis (Box 1)
    Reprint from Journal of American Medical Women's Association, 16: 12 (Dec. 1961) pp. 942-945, "Chronic Brucellosis: The Unreliability of Diagnostic Tests" by ACE; correspondence from university medical centers, government offices, and individuals thanking ACE for the reprint and commenting on brucellosis. (1961-1964, 27 pcs.).
  - ACE, Correspondence, 1908-1965 (Box 1)
    The bulk of the correspondence pertains to ACE's disposal of books, prints, etc. Included is a form letter signed by Mary R. Beard, thanking ACE for items she contributed to the World Center for Women's Archives (Nov. 22, 1939); also a letter from ACE to her parents (1908) describing the amusements of a group of about 30 women students living in Alumnae House on Eddy Street. (34 pcs.).
  - ACE, Correspondence, 1922-1929, 1930-1934 (Box 1)
    Correspondence pertaining to ACE's work and interest in various diseases, especially brucellosis and others transmitted through animals' milk; a report by ACE on the Women's Industrial Conference (Jan. 1926, 2 pp. carbon typescript); and other items. (176 pcs. in two folders).
  - ACE, Correspondence, 1935-1940 (Box 1)
    Correspondence pertaining to research on various diseases, especially chronic brucellosis, and to human infection through milk consumption; a letter from Carrie Chapman Catt (Nov. 18, 1940) asking ACE to be present at a meeting honoring women following careers they could not have followed 50 years earlier; a 6 pp. pamphlet, Women's Centennial Congress, 1840-1940 (held Nov. 26, 1940); and other items. (110 pcs.).
  - ACE, Correspondence, 1941-1949 (Box 1)
    Correspondence pertaining to ACE's research on brucellosis and other subjects; a letter from a serviceman who had received a "psychoneurotic" discharge and wished to be cleared of the stigma, believing that his symptoms were caused by brucellosis; answering letters from ACE to the above and similar letters from other individuals; and other items. (43 pcs.).
  - ACE, Correspondence, 1950-1965 (Box 1)
    Correspondence pertaining to ACE's work on brucellosis; copies of extracts from correspondence with Theobald Smith (May-Dec. 1925) concerning their disagreement about the possibility of human infection through bovine organisms; material pertaining to brucellosis (undulant fever) to Professor E.V. McCollum of Johns Hopkins; and other items. (70 pcs.).
- Photographs
  - Two photographs of ACE, 1934 and 1942. Also, a photograph of ACE ( 1912 ) is attached to a letter of May 30, 1956. (Box 1)
- Addendum
  - Some correspondence for early 1935 (above) concerns Evans's participation in a "Conference on Fields of Work for Women," sponsored by the Federation of Cornell Women's Clubs, Mar. 9, 1935. Included is a typed copy of the address she gave there about opportunities for women in medicine. (Box 2)
  - Publications, 1912-1961. (Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee report on Foot and Mouth Disease and Studies on Foot and Mouth Disease, 1974, 1966 (Box 2)